A Guide to the Fugitive Slave Fund: Claims for Payment, 1857-1860
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Fugitive Slave Fund: Claims for Payment, 1857-1860
The Library of Virginia
APA 689
.20 cu. ft (1 box)
Auditor of Public Accounts
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
No acquisition information available.
Biographical Information
On March 17, 1856 the General Assembly passed an act for preventing the escape of enslaved people entitled "An Act providing additional protection for the slave property of citizens of this commonwealth.” This act authorized the inspection of ships departing from Virginia, rewards of up to $500 to any white person who provided information leading to the conviction of any other white person who attempted to help an enslaved person escape, or the apprehension and arrest of escaped enslaved people. The reward was paid by either the slave holder and/or state upon the order of the court convicting the party of such offense, provided the conviction was due to the testimony of someone other than the informer.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of records from 1857 to 1860, including the following: warrants for payment submitted to the Auditor of Public Accounts, responses to said warrants, and signed testimonies and affidavits affirming their right to payment.
The testimonies and affidavits list the individual entitled to a reward, and the reason for it. Typically, these men sought payment for either apprehending enslaved people who had "absconded," or for providing information on individuals who assisted or aided enslaved people in their escape. A significant portion of these cases took place in the northern part of Virginia as the enslaved people escaped to either Pennsylvania or Ohio before being apprehended. The records list the enslaved people, who owned them, and occasionally an assigned value in order to calculate the payment owed by the state.
Payment requests ranged from $50 to $1500, but not all of them were honored. Some records include responses from the Auditor of Public Accounts noting that there was no money in the fund to disperse.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Fugitive Slave Fund: Claims for Payment, 1857-1860., Extent: 1 box. (Box 1, Folder 1-17)
  - James Adams, 1857 June 11. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Request for payment for the apprehension of Henry in Carlisle, Pennsylvania. Henry was enslaved by the company Rust and Trundle.
  - Henry Chappell, 1857 Aug 28. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Request for payment for providing information leading to conviction of John McKinney, who "was engaged in carrying off a slave named Anna." Anna was enslaved by Joel Ruffner.
  - Luther Kurtz, 1857 Oct 2. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Request for payment to Jerome D. Brumbaugh on behalf of Kurtz for the apprehension of several enslaved people including: Mary, enslaved by Isabella Gray; Eliza, Philip, and Franny who were enslaved by Charles Douglas.
  - Samuel Bowman, Daniel Ragan, and Jonathan Clary, 1857 Nov 25. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Request for payment to these three men for providing information on Thomas Dunn. Dunn attempted to "carry" Oliver, who was enslaved by Thomas Mosby, out of Lynchburg.
  - James Murdaugh, 1858 May 11. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Request for payment for providing information on Edward Lee, who was convicted for "carrying off" an enslaved woman named Isabella or "Bell." Isabella was enslaved by James Murdaugh.
  - J.D. Kinsley and M.W. Housen, 1858 Oct 22. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Request for payment for the apprehension of Henry and Betsey, who were located in Pennsylvania. They were enslaved by J.B. Robertson.
  - Henry Loyd and Elisha McCutcheon, 1858 Dec 20. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Request for payment for the apprehension of Isaac who was located in the state of Ohio. He was enslaved by Joseph Friend.
  - John Harbaugh and Lewis Harbaugh, 1859 Jan 7. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Request for payment to J.D. Brumbaugh on behalf of the Harbaughs. They apprehended an enslaved man named Washington, enslaved by N.W. Ford, in the state of Pennsylvania.
  - William Wilson, Joseph Carter, and James G. Hodges, 1859 Feb 4. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Request for payment to three men for informing the courts of the previously mentioned Edward Lee. In this instance Lee attempted to "carry off" Anthony, Bob, Jack, and Stetney who were enslaved by Wilson, Carter, and Hodges.
  - John L. Griffith, 1859 Apr 11. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Request for payment for the apprehension of John Jackson, enslaved by Cadwalader Chapman. Jackson was apprehended in the state of Ohio.
  - William H. Gaines, 1859 May 30. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Request for payment for providing information leading to the apprehension of John Shuman. Shuman was arrested for assisting Ned Nelson "abscond" from Enoch Jeffries.
  - Fountain F. Henry, 1859 June 20. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Request for payment for providing information leading to the apprehension and conviction of William N. Ceate for advising an enslaved man, Seth, to abscond from John C. Major.
  - Joseph Kinsell, 1859 Aug 18. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Request for payment for the apprehension of two enslaved people who had escaped to Pennsylvania. They were George, who was enslaved by George Weaver, and John, who was enslaved by William Cunningham. This document also mentions the previous arrest of a man named William who was enslaved by someone named Harris.
  - A.J. Longsdorff, 1859 Sept 8. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Request for payment for the apprehension of John, who escaped James Richards, and fled to Pennsylvania.
  - Abram Henkle, 1859 Oct 10. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Request for payment for providing information that led to the arrest and conviction of Absalom Nelson. Nelson was arrested for "feloniously aiding and advising slaves to abscond" from Michael Henkle.
  - Joseph Kinsell, 1859 Nov 14. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Request for payment for apprehension of William who was located in the state of Pennsylvania. William was enslaved by Gabriel Harris.
  - R. L. Montague, 1860 Mar 27. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Request for payment for information on Capt. John Minkuis of the schooner Mary Priscilla, Capt. Robert Woten of the schooner Mahlon, and Captain Jacob Simmons of the schooner Alicia for violating inspection law. The parties were found not guilty, but a petition was still made for payment due to the work Montague put in.